Guide to the Denominational Ministry Strategy Collection, 1973-1995 AIS.1989.07
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Denominational Ministry Strategy Collection
1973-1995
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Denominational Ministry Strategy Pittsburgh Coalition
AIS.1989.07
6.25 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
The Denominational Ministry Strategy (DMS) was formed by a group of Pittsburgh clergymen early in 1982. The original mission of the organization was to assist the newly unemployed steelworkers of the Monongahela Valley and to make the state and local government aware of their plight. In addition to correspondence and newspaper clippings, there is also much polemical material directed against the business and investment decisions of Mellon Bank, U.S. Steel, Dravo and other large Pittsburgh corporations which the group believed had failed in their responsibilities to the communities of workers who had made them prosperous. Many documents in the collection articulate theological and moral positions which attempt to ground the group's political action within the Christian scriptural tradition. Court transcripts documenting the legal battles of the DMS and of Rev. D. Douglas Roth, who was defrocked by the Lutheran Church for his participation in the organization, are also present.
History
The Denominational Ministry Strategy (DMS) was formed by a group of Pittsburgh clergymen early in 1982 to assist the newly unemployed steelworkers of the Monongahela Valley and to make state and local government aware of their plight. The DMS followed in the footsteps of past groups such as the Pittsburgh Coalition and the Metropolitan Citizens Organization in that various congregations from the Pittsburgh area banded together in response to changes within their community. After initial efforts by the DMS yielded few results, the group altered its tactics to draw attention to the problems of the unemployed. Joining with the local union activists of the Network to Save the Mon/Ohio Valley, the organization targeted banking and manufacturing corporations within Pittsburgh as the primary reason behind the region's deindustrialization. Some of their protests included removing their money from branches of Mellon Bank and placing fish in Mellon bank boxes, symbolizing that there was something fishy about the institution. This approach brought the group into conflict with the Lutheran Church in America, which initially supported the DMS. Pastors D. Douglas Roth and Daniel Solberg were defrocked by the church in 1984 and 1985, respectively, due to their involvement with the group and both were jailed for refusing to give up their posts. Solberg's brother, actor David Soul, became involved in the work of the DMS and created, along with Bill Jersey, the 1986 PBS documentary, The Fighting Ministers, about their efforts. In 1987, the organization changed its name to the Denominational Ministry Strategy Extended (DMX) as a way of mocking U.S. Steel and their name change to USX. Later that year, the group evolved into the Confessing Synod Ministries in response to the opposition it received from the Lutheran Church. The group is still in operation as of 2007.
Scope and Content Notes
The records of the Denominational Ministry Strategy (DMS) cover the period from 1982 to 1994. In addition to correspondence and newspaper clippings, there is also much polemical material directed against the business and investment decisions of Mellon Bank, U.S. Steel, Dravo and other large Pittsburgh corporations which the group believed had failed in their responsibilities to the communities of workers who had made them prosperous. Many documents in the collection articulate theological and moral positions which attempt to ground the group's political action within the Christian scriptural tradition and also to link their conduct with the Protestant church resistance to Hitler (hence the future appropriation by the group of the term "Confessing Synod"). Correspondence concerning the business and personal matters of the DMS and its leaders are also present, along with photographs taken at DMS events. Polemics against the alleged corporate ties of the Lutheran Church in America and its Western Pennsylvania Synod emerge as another preoccupation as the DMS sought to defend the ministers and their mission in the face of disciplinary actions levied against them by Church authorities. Court transcripts documenting the legal battles of Rev. D. Douglas Roth, who was defrocked by the Lutheran Church, as well as many newspaper clippings regarding Roth and the efforts of the DMS, are included. There are also records from the organization's predecessor, The Pittsburgh Coalition, which was active from 1976 to 1979. Year books of the Metropolitan Citizens Organization (MCO), a citizen action group led by DMS trainer Charles Honeywell that was active from 1978 to 1982, are also present.
Arrangement
Series I. Founding and Organizational Documents, 1975-1989
Series II. Newsletters, 1986-1995
Series III. Media and Press Releases, 1982-1987
Series IV. Legal Documents, 1984-1994
Series V. Correspondence, 1973-1993
Series VI. Publications, 1976-1994
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Charles Honeywell on June 21, 1989. Additional deposits were made on October 22, 1992; January 25, 1993; October 11, 1993; and April 21, 1995.
Previous Citation
Denominational Ministry Strategy Collection, 1973-1995, AIS.1989.07, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Archival Material
Rosenberg, David L., "Pittsburgh in Revolt: Sources and Artifacts of the Struggle against Deindustrialization from the UEL/Labor Archives at the University of Pittsburgh," Pennsylvania History, 68 (Summer 2001): 367–82.
Industrial Union of Marine and Shipbuilding Workers of America, Local 61 Records, 1943-1988, AIS.1989.05, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh
Separated Material
Photographs taken by Pittsburgh Post-Gazette photographer Harry Coughenour, as well as video cassettes of The Fighting Ministers and news footage can be found in the Media Storage room.
Labor; Deindustrialization -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Unemployment -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Press releases; Legal documents; Newsletters; Correspondence; Lutheran Church -- Clergy; Social action; Clairton (Pa.); Associations; Dravo Corporation; Honeywell, Charles; Lutheran Church in America; May, Kenneth R.; Mellon Bank Corporation; Roth, Dewey Douglas; Solberg, Daniel N.; Soul, David; United States Steel Corporation; Denominational Ministry Strategy Pittsburgh Coalition
- Founding and Organizational Documents, 1975-1989; I.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains information regarding the founding of the Denominational Ministry Strategy (DMS) and its predecessors, the Pittsburgh Coalition and Metropolitan Citizens Organization. Included are mission statements, meeting minutes, yearbooks, and correspondence from the organizations' founders. Papers on Mellon Bank, U.S. Steel, and the Network to Save the Mon/Ohio Valley are also present and provide an overview of their relationship with the DMS.
  - Pittsburgh Coalition, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pittsburgh Coalition Founding and Organizational Documents, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Pittsburgh Coalition Correspondence, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pittsburgh Coalition Meeting Minutes, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pittsburgh Coalition Newsletters and Mailings, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Metropolitan Citizens Organization Yearbook, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Denominational Ministry Strategy Founding and Organizational Documents, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Denominational Ministry Strategy Ideological and Theological Documents, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Denominational Ministry Strategy, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 09-11)
  - Mellon Bank, 1977-1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - U.S. Steel/USX, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Network to Save the Mon/Ohio Valley, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Confessing Synod Ministries, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Denominational Ministry Strategy Extended, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Newsletters, 1986-1995; II.
  The newsletters in this series document the activities of the DMS, DMX, and Confessing Synod Ministries. Many of the activities are concerned with the deindustrialization of Pittsburgh in the 1980s and include information on actions taken against Mellon Bank, Dravo Corporation, and U.S. Steel. Newsletters from the Christ Lutheran Church and St. Matthew's Episcopal Church, both members of the DMS, are also included.
  - Christ Lutheran Church, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Voice of the Valley, St. Matthew's Episcopal Church, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Denominational Ministry Strategy, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Denominational Ministry Strategy, January - April 1988 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Confessing Synod Ministries, 1988-1995 (Box 1, Folder 21-25)
- Press and Media Releases, 1982-1987; III.
  This series contains press releases regarding the activities of the DMS and the companies the DMS held responsible for Pittsburgh's high unemployment in the 1980s. Many of the press releases are concerned with protests mounted jointly by the DMS and the Network to Save the Mon/Ohio Valley and the actions of corporate executives from Mellon Bank and U.S. Steel. Also included are examples of pamphlets which would be distributed throughout Pittsburgh communities concerning the high unemployment rates and economic fall of the region.
  - Press Releases and Announcements, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Press Releases, January 1984 - January 1987 (Box 2, Folder 02-08)
  - Community Releases,1985-1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 09-10)
- Legal Documents, 1984-1994; IV.
  The documents in this series are concerned mainly with the legal troubles of Rev. D. Douglas Roth. Early in 1984, Roth was removed from his position at the Trinity Lutheran Church in Clairton, Pa., by the bishop of the Western Pennsylvania-West Virginia Synod of the Lutheran Church in America. Roth ignored the order so that he would be granted a disciplinary hearing before church authorities to plead his case; however, the bishop filed a civil court complaint instead. Roth was jailed in contempt of court for failing to appear at his hearing and for conducting services. He remained in jail for several months because he refused to sign a paper that would end his term at Trinity Lutheran Church. Also included are legal documents regarding the DMX's resistance to developers George and Damien Zamias erecting a shopping mall in Frazer Township, Pa.
  - Bishop Kenneth May and Western PA - West Virginia Synod v. Trinity Lutheran Church and D. Douglas Roth, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 11-15)
  - Commonwealth v. D. Douglas Roth v. Rev. William Rex Jr. Transcript, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bishop Kenneth May and Western PA-West Virginia Synod v. Trinity Lutheran Church, D. Douglas Roth and Nadine Roth Transcript, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bishop Kenneth May and Western PA-West Virginia Synod v. Trinity Lutheran Church, D. Douglas Roth and Nadine Roth Transcript, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Commonwealth v. Dewey Douglas Roth Transcript, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - Bishop Kenneth May and Western PA-West Virginia Synod v. Trinity Lutheran Church, D. Douglas Roth and Nadine Roth Legal Documents, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Motion for the Release of Rev. Roth, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Bishop Kenneth May and Western PA-West Virginia Synod v. Trinity Lutheran Church and Rev. D. Douglas Roth and Members Injunction, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - George and Damien Zamias v. Denominational Ministry Strategy Extended Legal Documents, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Motion for the Release of Rev. Roth, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1973-1993; V.
  This series contains correspondence from various members of the DMS concerning their activities within the Pittsburgh region. Many of these documents are concerned with the actions of Bishop Kenneth May against the DMS and its leaders, such as Rev. Roth, Rev. Solberg, and Rev. Gropp. There are several messages from Rev. Solberg to various judges in Allegheny County that he sent while serving time in prison, as well as correspondence regarding Rev. Roth's court hearings. Also included are letters from the United Steel Workers of America and the Industrial Union of Marine and Shipbuilding Workers of America to members of the DMS about their efforts regarding unemployment in the Mon Valley.
  - Miscellaneous, 1978-1993 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General, 1976-1986 (Box 3, Folder 03-09)
  - Bishop Kenneth R. May, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
  - Bishop James Crumley, Lutheran Church of America, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Rev. Daniel Solberg, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Pastor Phillip D. Long, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Rev. James Von Dreele, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Bishop Will Herzfeld, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Rev. Martin Buerger, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - John H. Tietjen, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Nativity Lutheran Church, Allison Park, PA, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Christ Lutheran Church, Duquesne, PA, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Rev. D. Douglas Roth regarding Court Cases, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Mellon Bank, 1973-1987 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - United Steelworkers of America, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Media, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Industrial Union of Marine and Shipbuilding Workers of America, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - State and Local Government, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Lutheran Church in America Convention and Freedom Ride, 1986-1993 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Baptists, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Other Organizations, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Amnesty International, 1982-1988 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - South Africa, 1985-1989 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Publications, 1976-1994; VI.
  This series includes press clippings from local newspapers such as the Pittsburgh Press and Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, as well as The Wall Street Journal, The New York Times, and USA Today, regarding the efforts of the DMS and the Network to Save the Mon/Ohio Valley. The clippings include cartoons, letters to the editor, and feature articles about DMS activities, Rev. Roth's defrocking and arrest, and the state of the steel industry in Pittsburgh. Other documents include flyers and pamphlets distributed by the DMS and papers regarding the film The Fighting Ministers. A copy of the film, as well as a tape containing news features on the DMS, is also present. Photographs taken by Pittsburgh Post-Gazette photographer Harry Coughenour at DMS activities are included.
  - Miscellaneous Flyers and Pamphlets, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - The Basic Bible for Real People, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - The Book on Pittsburgh, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - The Fighting Ministers, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Pittsburgh Magazine Feature Article "Steeltown Radicals", undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Metropolitan Citizens Organization Clippings, 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Denominational Ministry Strategy Clippings, 1983-May 1984 (Box 3, Folder 39-45)
  - Denominational Ministry Strategy Clippings, June 1984-1994 (Box 4, Folder 01-13)
  - Pittsburgh Post Gazette News Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 01-03)
  - The Fighting Ministers, undated (Box 5, Cassette 1)
  - Features from Nightline, 60 Minutes, 700 Club, and the Local News, undated (Box 5, Cassette 2)